This is my kitchen table and also my
filing system.
Over much of the past three decades,
I've been an investor the highest
calling of mankind I've often thought
was private equity.
And then I started interviewing.
Oh, I watch your interview with coach.
I know how to do something.
I've learned in doing my interviews how
leaders make it to the top.
I asked him how much you want.
He said to 50.
I said, Fine.
I didn't negotiate with him.
I didn't know due diligence.
I have something I'd like to sell and
how they stay there.
You don't feel inadequate now because
being only the second wealthiest man in
the world, Is that right?
At the Bloomberg house in Davos.
I recently had a chance to sit down with
Al Gore.
Former vice President United States had
a chance to ask him what it was like to
come so close to being president but not
actually becoming president.
I also asked him why spending so much
time on clean energy and cleaning up the
environment.
So today you're spending a fair amount
of your time on your investment
operation.
You make a lot of speeches.
You're also involved on the board of the
World Economic Forum, where we are today
in Davos.
What propelled you to go on the board of
the World Economic Forum?
Klaus Schwab, the former chairman and
the founder of the with the World
Economic Forum, called me and asked me
to join after I wrote a book called The
Future Six Drivers of Global Change.
It turned out that Klaus Schwab was the
target demographic for that for that
book, and he liked it a lot and called
me and asked me to join the board.
You are an advocate for climate change
and that people should pay more
attention to it.
What do you think people can
realistically do to do more about
climate change than we're doing?
And have?
You might talk about the Paris Accords,
because under the Paris Accords, as I
understand it, when it was set up that
the goal was to get the the temperature,
the Celsius temperature not to go up by
the year 2100 by more than, let's say,
1.4 degrees.
And now we're on track to go to two or
two and a half times our two and a half
degrees Celsius.
So in other words, by 2100, if we did
nothing, the theory was you go to four
degrees higher, four degrees Celsius
higher, and that would be catastrophic.
How close are we going to get to the
original goal of, let's say, one point
to 1.3, 1.4, We can overshoot and then
come back down if we stop adding more
heat trapping pollution to the
atmosphere and stabilize at what they
call net zero.
The temperature will stop going up
immediately.
It's a thermostatic system and the
thermostat is not a round knob on the
wall.
It's the set of policies that currently
include massive subsidies for fossil
fuels.
If we didn't subsidize fossil fuels and
forced the taxpayers to subsidize them,
they would be gone pretty quickly if
fossil fuels had not been discovered on
the face of the earth, there had been no
oil and gas.
Do you think civilization would be
further ahead of where it is or we'd be
behind?
Because fossil fuels are unable to do
many things we otherwise couldn't do?
Yeah, no question about it.
And we owe the men and women in in the
fossil fuel industry for helping create
the civilization that we enjoyed today.
And they did not know until 50 years
ago, at least, that the byproduct, this
heat trapping pollution was going to
cause such problems.
And, you know, just to pause on this for
a moment, David.
Yesterday, 300,000 people were forced
from their homes in Mozambique.
50,000 people two days ago were forced
from their homes by these massive
downpours in South Africa.
Three days ago in Chile, massive fires
contribute connected to the climate
crisis.
Last year in the U.S., we had 12 once in
a thousand year downpours in a space in
the space of three days.
We had the Los Angeles fires in my home
state of Tennessee and even more so in
neighboring North Carolina.
The downpour associated with that
massive hurricane Helene.
We got more rain in four days than falls
over the largest waterfall in the world
in two and a half years.
And it's getting steadily worse.
Beyond that, there are very tiny areas
in the world today that are
physiologically unlivable in the Sahara
Desert, a few places around the Persian
Gulf.
The combination of heat and humidity
makes it impossible for people to live
for more than four or 5 hours outdoors.
Those areas are now beginning to expand
dramatically.
And the World Health Organization's
Climate Committee says that by 2050, we
could have 1 to 2 billion climate
migrants crossing international borders,
a few million coming from the eastern
Mediterranean with the climate drought
there led to Viktor Orban and Brexit and
authoritarian friendly governments that
have emerged.
It's hard to imagine what a billion
climate migrants would do to our
capacity for self governance, and we're
in danger of crossing some so-called
negative tipping points like the
shutting down of the Gulf Stream.
Sounds like a science fiction movie.
And it was, But it's now a very real
threat.
And there are others.
We are now trapping as much heat with
this pollution every day as would be
released by 750,000 Hiroshima class
bombs, atomic bombs exploding every 24
hours.
You've been vice president, nine states.
You've won the Nobel Peace Prize without
lobbying for
who would do that?
You won the Academy Award for your
picture on the environment.
You've been a senator, vice president,
member of Congress.
Why are you so driven at this point to
worry about climate change?
You've done so many things in your life.
I mean, climate change is an important
thing, but let's some other people
don't.
Why are you so driven on this subject?
First of all, a minor detail.
I always give Davis Guggenheim credit
for the Academy Award.
He was the director I have visiting
rights to the Academy Award.
But why am I so driven?
Well.
Oh, when I was
very young, when I was a college
student,
first of all, I had no idea that climate
was going to be take over my life to the
extent that it has.
But I had in
my last year in college, a course under
a man now recognized as one of the
greatest climate scientists of all time,
Roger Revelle.
And he opened my eyes to the issue and
educated me.
And it was like a window opening on to
the future.
And everything that he said at the time
has come true.
Unfortunately, he designed the first
experiment to measure CO2 in the Earth's
atmosphere.
And David Keeling, a scientist who
created what's called the Keeling Curve,
that's the bedrock of modern climate
science.
Anyway, I was first introduced to the
issue back when I was very young, 20
years old, and later when I got to the
Congress, well, I kept in touch with
Professor Revelle and I stayed close to
him.
When I was elected to Congress, I
started asking, What are we doing about
what we call global warming then?
And the answer was crickets.
Or, you know, nobody had really heard of
it to any extent.
I finally got permission to hold the
first congressional hearing in the House
on climate, and I invited my professor
to be the lead off witness.
And I naively thought that his statement
would create the same epiphany for my
colleagues on the dias that a full
college course had created for me.
And that did not happen at all.
And in the aftermath of that hearing, I
first asked myself the question, how can
how can I recreate the aha moment that I
had and explain this in a way that takes
this great scientist's message to others
because it's so critical.
David And it's the kind of challenge
where once you pick it up, you really
can't put it down because it's such a
threat.
It has to be dealt.
So when you were a young man, you
decided to go to Harvard College and
your father was a United States senator
from Tennessee.
You went to Harvard and your roommate
was Tommy Lee Jones.
And what he was more famous at the time,
I guess.
Well, he was a great football player at
the time and a great student actor.
And we remained great friends to this
day.
So after you graduated, most people in
your generation, which was my
generation, figured out, how can I not
go into the Vietnam War and how can I
not go into the military?
Obviously some people did and they
deserve credit for it.
But you
enlisted, you volunteered.
You didn't wait to be drafted.
Why did you enlist?
And didn't that cause a lot of concern
on your family's part?
Certainly on my mother's part.
Yes.
I was raised in two places.
My father was in the Congress, House and
Senate.
So I spent a lot of time in D.C.
as a child.
But every summer and Christmas and my
spiritual home was in Carthage,
Tennessee, and that's where my draft
board was.
And I couldn't imagine walking down the
street and seeing a family whose son had
died in Vietnam and them knowing that I
had used some connections to get out of
it.
There was another factor I have to add,
that helped to clarify the issue for me,
and that is my father was a leading
opponent of the Vietnam War and I was
immensely proud of him and his
reelection was coming up and getting out
of Vietnam did not seem like the most
honorable thing for me to do, and it
didn't seem like the most beneficial
thing for my dad either.
So I decided that the right thing to do
was to go ahead and volunteer.
I went in as a private and went to
Vietnam.
After you got out of military service,
you went to divinity school.
Were you thinking of being a preacher or
something?
I was not.
I was raised in a churchgoing family,
but at the age of 21, I felt very
strongly the moral dilemma of being
opposed to the Vietnam War, marching in
opposition to the Vietnam War, and then
how could you go and be a part of it?
I had my reasons, and I thought they
were sound and valid, but I worried
about it.
You know, when you're that young, you
can build these things up in your mind.
And I thought that coming back to the US
after the war, it would be healthy and
good for me to have a structured
environment where I could explore the
ethical questions that I had focused on.
So you didn't complete divinity school.
You went to journalism school for a
while.
And I don't know.
I thought you went to journalism.
No, I went to when I came back from
Vietnam, I got a job $95 a week working
as a cub reporter for the Nashville
Tennessean.
You may have known John Siegenthaler, a
great editor who was my mentor.
And then I went to divinity school at
the same time.
And as a journalist, I benefited a great
deal from Siegenthaler tutoring.
I became an investigative journalist and
got into corruption and local and state
government corruption in local and state
government.
It's hard to believe, I know.
But even even back then, it occasionally
appeared to two Councilman.
I got indicted and one of them was
convicted.
The the lawsuits I was in, I was a
witness in a couple of trials, and I
saw, oh, boy, this law thing.
I need to know more about this.
My parents were both lawyers, so there
was that.
But I decided to go to law school,
continued to work at the newspaper, and
I thought that I would maybe be Fred
Graham.
Do you remember Fred Graham?
He was the Supreme Court reporter, first
for The New York Times and CBS.
He was a kind of a role model for me in
those days.
But you didn't complete law school?
No, because at the end of my second
year, the congressional seat in my home
district came open.
There was a surprise retirement, and I
packed up and just started running for
Congress.
On the spur of the moment.
I surprised myself in some ways as
somebody who did finish law school, I
can tell you, you didn't miss anything.
I always felt I always felt guilty about
not finishing it.
Don't feel guilty about that.
So you were a successful member of
Congress.
You then ran for the Senate.
You got elected to the Senate.
And then in 1988, you ran for president
and you didn't win.
I was 38 years old.
And in some dictionaries, I'm told if
you look up the word Hudspeth, you'll
see a picture of my announcement speech.
Oh, 38 years old.
You didn't get elected come third place
on the Democratic side, but so you
considered running again.
Dukakis was the nominee.
He lost fairly decisively to George
Herbert Walker Bush in 92.
You thought about running again and you
cited not to.
Why did you not run again?
You were your old.
And you had more experience.
Why did you run?
Not run in 92?
In April of 1989.
One of my children had a very, very
serious ax.
Your son?
My son almost lost his life and the
recovery was quite lengthy.
And the stress and strain on the family,
of course, it in a car.
A car, it hit him.
He was hit by a car.
Went to your beloved Orioles in
Baltimore.
And after the game, I hate to tell you,
I was rooting for the Red Sox in that
game, but but afterwards, he was hit by
a car.
It was a it was a devastating experience
in so many ways.
I was worried when I got to him that he
had died.
His everything turned out great.
He's fantastic.
When the 92 campaign approached, I was
still as a dad
in the midst of taking care of my
family.
All right.
So then Bill Clinton gets the nomination
for president, and then he he's a
Southerner, obviously.
And did you ever think he would pick
another Southerner to be his vice
presidential candidate?
And did you think twice about ever
becoming vice president when he asked
you?
I never expected that he would pick me.
No, because the tradition up until that
time had been in both parties to balance
the ticket geographically, ideologically
and so forth.
And Bill and I were from neighboring
states in the Upper South in the same
part of the ideological spectrum.
We had advocated for a centrism approach
at the Democratic Party and never
thought he would do it.
But
I was at the Earth Summit in Rio de
Janeiro during the Senate delegation on
climate when I got the call, and I still
didn't think it was very serious, but we
had a terrific set of conversations.
And then did I did I think twice about
accepting that invitation?
I did, actually.
But my conversations with Bill went so
well that I'm glad that I did it.
All right.
She served as vice president for eight
years.
Then you decide to run for president.
But you got immersed in the private
sector and you went on the board of
Apple.
MM.
What was your qualification to be on the
board of Apple?
Well, good question.
But I had become friends with Steve Jobs
when he was at his first tour at Apple,
and I was a young congressman who one of
the sponsors of legislation to ease his
donation of computers to schools.
And we became friends And I had worked
on networking issues and technology
issues.
When I became vice president, I got a
commitment from President Clinton that I
would handle technology and the
environment, and he kept his word on
that.
And I was deeply involved with the
computer industry.
So you also started an investment
company?
Yeah.
And nothing could be more important than
it being an investor, Right.
I learned from you.
Right.
So you started investment company, but
had the the concept that you would
invest only companies that did things
that were good for society.
All right.
It's a very novel concept and it
actually worked out so far.
Yeah, very much so.
And I learned that my secret to success
and business is to get great partners.
And David Blood, my co-founder, the old
joke is I've worn it out.
Really.
I wanted to name the firm Blood and
Gore, but the other the other partners
wouldn't wouldn't agree to it.
But when I first left the the the the
the White House in January of 2001 and
voluntarily, I got an offer from another
investment firm.
And it's common you went through this
transition from the White House to the
private sector yourself and the salaries
in the private sector are a little
bigger than you get.
They are in public service.
And but I didn't really enjoy it.
They were great people, but it was just
about making money.
And I hope that doesn't sound weird, but
it didn't get my passions flowing and I
learned the business and decided I'd
like to find a way to to set it up in
alignment with the principles that I
felt are so important.
We don't invest in fossil fuels.
I urge you not to do it too, by the way.
But everybody else does it.
Well, you'll think about it.
I hope you will, because I hope we can
come back to climate.
It's way more serious than people
realize.
But in any case, at the end of that
first gig in investing,
I
had been fortunate enough to go to work
for Google right out of the the White
House, and that was a good move as it
turned out.
And I went to try to set up my own
investment firm, and that's when I met
David Blood.
He was retiring from Goldman Sachs, and
we set up this firm 21 years ago, and
now it's had a higher rate of return
than the S&P 500, I gather, over that
We've had a we've had a lot of success.
The the people who work with us are
fantastic.
And if you if you.
Set it up in the way you do.
We're we we invest everything through a
sustainability lens that attracts the
brightest and best people to come knock
on your door and want to work with you.
I have a terrific group that I worked
with.
When you were called and told you you
and a few others had won the Nobel Peace
Prize, were you thinking it was a
mistake or a joke or because you hadn't
been campaigning for it and it wasn't?
Climate change wasn't considered a peace
prize kind of thing at the time.
So were you surprised or you kind of
knew maybe it might happen?
A little of both.
I was surprised.
But in the days leading up to it, there
had been some buzz about that
possibility.
So when the actual announcement came at
2:00 in the morning, I was waiting up to
what's the news.
But you haven't given your Nobel Peace
Prize to anybody else, right?
I don't know.
I you know, I hadn't even thought of
doing that.
Actually, I've devoted a lot of time to
trying to raise awareness of why we have
to solve the climate crisis.
And we do have to do it.
We really don't have any choice about
this.
Do.
Is there anything that humans today can
do?
Yes.
That will change the lives of the humans
currently on the earth.
In other words.
Yeah.
Things you do now might affect my great
grandchildren.
Maybe it'll help them.
But today, why should I do something
that I'm not going to get the benefit
of?
Yeah,
well, first of all, people who switch
over are getting the benefit right away.
But coming back to the point about the
fossil fuel industry and our debt to
them.
There's an old saying that came from
King of Saudi Arabia years ago.
The Stone Age didn't end because of a
shortage of stones.
It ended because something better came
along.
Something better has come along now to
replace fossil fuels which are dirty and
polluting and threatening humanity's
future.
The cheapest electricity in the history
of the world is solar energy.
Second cheapest is wind energy and now
batteries that the only things come down
in price faster than solar is utility
scale batteries doubling every single.
Why are we ending the wind farms that
are now being built off the coast of the
United States?
We're ending them because Trump is
insane.
On another subject.
You don't you don't want to explore
that.
But
let me let me let let me let me add one
point on on the solar.
If I asked you
it's not a trick question, but if you
look at all of the new electricity
generation installed worldwide last
year, I often ask people what percentage
of it was renewable.
And people say, you know, they're
looking for a high number, so maybe 30%,
35% correct answer is 93%
because it is taking over the
electricity generation industry EVs from
a standing start.
Two decades ago, one quarter of all the
new cars cars sold last year were EVs.
60% last month.
You drive in TV.
Pardon?
I do, Yes.
Okay.
What do you.
You're a very serious person.
You've done all these great things in
your life.
What do you do to relax?
I mean, can you just say, Look, I've
been vice president, I've won the Nobel
Peace Prize, I've won an Academy Award,
I've done all these things.
I'm just going to take some time off and
relax, you know, to relax or just chill
out.
I'm relaxing right now.
Really?
Okay.
All right.
But you have you have Great.
Yes, I do.
Enjoy.
What do you do when you're relaxing?
I see you have cowboy boots on, are you?
You're not from Texas.
How come you have cowboy boots?
Well, these came from my brother in law
40 years ago, and they're so molded to
my feet.
They're the most comfortable shoes I
have.
But don't take them off at night or
just.
They're just really sleep.
I thought about sleeping in them, but
probably don't.
You asked about grandchildren.
Very proud of having ten grandchildren.
Ten?
Yeah.
Can you remember all their names?
Of course.
And how do you remember their birthdays?
You must have a I do a pretty good on
that.
Really?
Yeah.
Any of them want to run for office?
Well, I don't think so.
I think some of them would be great
candidates if they chose to.
I don't think they're really drawn to
that.
Right.
So in this long and very impressive
career, what would you say you're most
proud of having achieved in your life?
What would you say to your ten
grandchildren?
This is what your grandfather did that
you should be proud of?
Well, helping raised my four kids and
helping them raise my ten grandchildren
is what I would be most proud of in
terms of my professional activities and
political activities.
I've devoted a lot of time to trying to
raise awareness of why we have to solve
the climate crisis, and we do have to do
it.
We really don't have any choice about
this.
I look back on the work that I was
privileged to be able to do with
President Reagan on nuclear arms control
when I was in the House, and in the
first year in the Senate, I looked back
at the Reinventing Government program
and the work on computer networking.
Also very impressive career.
Thank you very much for being here and
good luck on everything you're doing on
climate change.
Thank you, David.
Thank you.
Thank you, You.